<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <link href="http://arxiv.org/api/query?search_query%3Dti%3A%5C%22Data%20Science%5C%22%26id_list%3D%26start%3D0%26max_results%3D10" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <title type="html">ArXiv Query: search_query=ti:\"Data Science\"&amp;id_list=&amp;start=0&amp;max_results=10</title>
  <id>http://arxiv.org/api/sUlz54Ju9IGKAl/IWxY9+OODAKo</id>
  <updated>2025-03-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <opensearch:totalResults xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">274616</opensearch:totalResults>
  <opensearch:startIndex xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">0</opensearch:startIndex>
  <opensearch:itemsPerPage xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">10</opensearch:itemsPerPage>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17690v1</id>
    <updated>2024-05-27T22:46:17Z</updated>
    <published>2024-05-27T22:46:17Z</published>
    <title>Data Makes Better Data Scientists</title>
    <summary>  With the goal of identifying common practices in data science projects, this
paper proposes a framework for logging and understanding incremental code
executions in Jupyter notebooks. This framework aims to allow reasoning about
how insights are generated in data science and extract key observations into
best data science practices in the wild. In this paper, we show an early
prototype of this framework and ran an experiment to log a machine learning
project for 25 undergraduate students.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Jinjin Zhao</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Avidgor Gal</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sanjay Krishnan</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17690v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.17690v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.HC" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.HC" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11086v1</id>
    <updated>2025-02-16T11:47:50Z</updated>
    <published>2025-02-16T11:47:50Z</published>
    <title>Data Ecofeminism</title>
    <summary>  Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI) is driving significant
environmental impacts. The rapid development and deployment of increasingly
larger algorithmic models capable of analysing vast amounts of data are
contributing to rising carbon emissions, water withdrawal, and waste
generation. Generative models often consume substantially more energy than
traditional models, with major tech firms increasingly turning to nuclear power
to sustain these systems -- an approach that could have profound environmental
consequences.
  This paper introduces seven data ecofeminist principles delineating a pathway
for developing technological alternatives of eco-societal transformations
within the AI research context. Rooted in data feminism and ecofeminist
frameworks, which interrogate about the historical and social construction of
epistemologies underlying the hegemonic development of science and technology
that disrupt communities and nature, these principles emphasise the integration
of social and environmental justice within a critical AI agenda. The paper
calls for an urgent reassessment of the GenAI innovation race, advocating for
ecofeminist algorithmic and infrastructural projects that prioritise and
respect life, the people, and the planet.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Ana Valdivia</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11086v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2502.11086v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.CY" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CY" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1401.0742v1</id>
    <updated>2014-01-03T22:15:17Z</updated>
    <published>2014-01-03T22:15:17Z</published>
    <title>Data Smashing</title>
    <summary>  Investigation of the underlying physics or biology from empirical data
requires a quantifiable notion of similarity - when do two observed data sets
indicate nearly identical generating processes, and when they do not. The
discriminating characteristics to look for in data is often determined by
heuristics designed by experts, $e.g.$, distinct shapes of "folded" lightcurves
may be used as "features" to classify variable stars, while determination of
pathological brain states might require a Fourier analysis of brainwave
activity. Finding good features is non-trivial. Here, we propose a universal
solution to this problem: we delineate a principle for quantifying similarity
between sources of arbitrary data streams, without a priori knowledge, features
or training. We uncover an algebraic structure on a space of symbolic models
for quantized data, and show that such stochastic generators may be added and
uniquely inverted; and that a model and its inverse always sum to the generator
of flat white noise. Therefore, every data stream has an anti-stream: data
generated by the inverse model. Similarity between two streams, then, is the
degree to which one, when summed to the other's anti-stream, mutually
annihilates all statistical structure to noise. We call this data smashing. We
present diverse applications, including disambiguation of brainwaves pertaining
to epileptic seizures, detection of anomalous cardiac rhythms, and
classification of astronomical objects from raw photometry. In our examples,
the data smashing principle, without access to any domain knowledge, meets or
exceeds the performance of specialized algorithms tuned by domain experts.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Ishanu Chattopadhyay</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hod Lipson</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1401.0742v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1401.0742v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.LG" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.AI" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.IT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.IT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.05039v1</id>
    <updated>2015-01-21T02:41:55Z</updated>
    <published>2015-01-21T02:41:55Z</published>
    <title>Defining Data Science</title>
    <summary>  Data science is gaining more and more and widespread attention, but no
consensus viewpoint on what data science is has emerged. As a new science, its
objects of study and scientific issues should not be covered by established
sciences. Data in cyberspace have formed what we call datanature. In the
present paper, data science is defined as the science of exploring datanature.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Yangyong Zhu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yun Xiong</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.05039v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1501.05039v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.DB" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.DB" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CY" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.05852v1</id>
    <updated>2022-01-15T13:51:12Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-15T13:51:12Z</published>
    <title>Data Science in Perspective</title>
    <summary>  Data and Science has stood out in the generation of results, whether in the
projects of the scientific domain or business domain. CERN Project, Scientific
Institutes, companies like Walmart, Google, Apple, among others, need data to
present their results and make predictions in the competitive data world. Data
and Science are words that together culminated in a globally recognized term
called Data Science. Data Science is in its initial phase, possibly being part
of formal sciences and also being presented as part of applied sciences,
capable of generating value and supporting decision making. Data Science
considers science and, consequently, the scientific method to promote decision
making through data intelligence. In many cases, the application of the method
(or part of it) is considered in Data Science projects in scientific domain
(social sciences, bioinformatics, geospatial projects) or business domain
(finance, logistic, retail), among others. In this sense, this article
addresses the perspectives of Data Science as a multidisciplinary area,
considering science and the scientific method, and its formal structure which
integrate Statistics, Computer Science, and Business Science, also taking into
account Artificial Intelligence, emphasizing Machine Learning, among others.
The article also deals with the perspective of applied Data Science, since Data
Science is used for generating value through scientific and business projects.
Data Science persona is also discussed in the article, concerning the education
of Data Science professionals and its corresponding profiles, since its
projection changes the field of data in the world.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Rogerio Rossi</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Information Society Conference - i-Society 2021</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.05852v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.05852v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.GL" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.GL" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1607.00858v1</id>
    <updated>2016-07-04T12:40:15Z</updated>
    <published>2016-07-04T12:40:15Z</published>
    <title>Embracing Data Science</title>
    <summary>  Statistics is running the risk of appearing irrelevant to today's
undergraduate students. Today's undergraduate students are familiar with data
science projects and they judge statistics against what they have seen.
Statistics, especially at the introductory level, should take inspiration from
data science so that the discipline is not seen as somehow lesser than data
science. This article provides a brief overview of data science, outlines ideas
for how introductory courses could take inspiration from data science, and
provides a reference to materials for developing stand-alone data science
courses.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Adam Loy</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">9 pages, 1 figure</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">The UMAP Journal 36 (2015) 285-292</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1607.00858v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1607.00858v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.GL" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1909.04486v1</id>
    <updated>2019-09-09T11:31:40Z</updated>
    <published>2019-09-09T11:31:40Z</published>
    <title>Data Science in Biomedicine</title>
    <summary>  We highlight the role of Data Science in Biomedicine. Our manuscript goes
from the general to the particular, presenting a global definition of Data
Science and showing the trend for this discipline together with the terms of
cloud computing and big data. In addition, since Data Science is mostly related
to areas like economy or business, we describe its importance in biomedicine.
Biomedical Data Science (BDS) presents the challenge of dealing with data
coming from a range of biological and medical research, focusing on
methodologies to advance the biomedical science discoveries, in an
interdisciplinary context.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Yovaninna Alarcón-Soto</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jenifer Espasandín-Domínguez</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ipek Guler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mercedes Conde-Amboage</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Francisco Gude-Sampedro</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Klaus Langohr</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Carmen Cadarso-Suárez</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Guadalupe Gómez-Melis</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1909.04486v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.04486v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1504.02878v1</id>
    <updated>2015-04-11T14:14:08Z</updated>
    <published>2015-04-11T14:14:08Z</published>
    <title>Data Science and Ebola</title>
    <summary>  Data Science---Today, everybody and everything produces data. People produce
large amounts of data in social networks and in commercial transactions.
Medical, corporate, and government databases continue to grow. Sensors continue
to get cheaper and are increasingly connected, creating an Internet of Things,
and generating even more data. In every discipline, large, diverse, and rich
data sets are emerging, from astrophysics, to the life sciences, to the
behavioral sciences, to finance and commerce, to the humanities and to the
arts. In every discipline people want to organize, analyze, optimize and
understand their data to answer questions and to deepen insights. The science
that is transforming this ocean of data into a sea of knowledge is called data
science. This lecture will discuss how data science has changed the way in
which one of the most visible challenges to public health is handled, the 2014
Ebola outbreak in West Africa.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Aske Plaat</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Inaugural lecture Leiden University</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1504.02878v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1504.02878v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.AI" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.AI" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CY" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.06324v1</id>
    <updated>2021-05-13T14:24:26Z</updated>
    <published>2021-05-13T14:24:26Z</published>
    <title>Perspective on Data Science</title>
    <summary>  The field of data science currently enjoys a broad definition that includes a
wide array of activities which borrow from many other established fields of
study. Having such a vague characterization of a field in the early stages
might be natural, but over time maintaining such a broad definition becomes
unwieldy and impedes progress. In particular, the teaching of data science is
hampered by the seeming need to cover many different points of interest. Data
scientists must ultimately identify the core of the field by determining what
makes the field unique and what it means to develop new knowledge in data
science. In this review we attempt to distill some core ideas from data science
by focusing on the iterative process of data analysis and develop some
generalizations from past experience. Generalizations of this nature could form
the basis of a theory of data science and would serve to unify and scale the
teaching of data science to large audiences.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Roger D. Peng</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hilary S. Parker</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.06324v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2105.06324v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.OT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.AP" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/cs/0505008v1</id>
    <updated>2005-05-02T15:27:45Z</updated>
    <published>2005-05-02T15:27:45Z</published>
    <title>Data Mining on Crash Simulation Data</title>
    <summary>  The work presented in this paper is part of the cooperative research project
AUTO-OPT carried out by twelve partners from the automotive industries. One
major work package concerns the application of data mining methods in the area
of automotive design. Suitable methods for data preparation and data analysis
are developed. The objective of the work is the re-use of data stored in the
crash-simulation department at BMW in order to gain deeper insight into the
interrelations between the geometric variations of the car during its design
and its performance in crash testing. In this paper a method for data analysis
of finite element models and results from crash simulation is proposed and
application to recent data from the industrial partner BMW is demonstrated. All
necessary steps from data pre-processing to re-integration into the working
environment of the engineer are covered.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>A. Kuhlmann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. -M. Vetter</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ch. Luebbing</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. -A. Thole</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">12 pages, 10 figures. Accepted for Lecture Notes in Computer Science
  (LNCS)</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Lecture Notes in Artificial
  Intelligence, Proceedings Conference MLDM 2005, Leipzig/Germany, Springer
  Verlag, LNAI 3587, ISBN: 3-540-26923-1, 2005</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cs/0505008v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/cs/0505008v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.IR" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.IR" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="H.2.8; D.2.2" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
</feed>